Hello everyone. Uh my name is Navid Kimi
and uh I'm very glad to be joined here
by uh professor Chatter and uh Dr. M Mc
M from uh
Warwick uh institute and mathematics
institute uh in the UK and they're going
to talk about thermal thermal
macroeconomics uh a thermal
thermodynamic approach to economics.
Uh so the first part of the talk would
be uh them going through the
presentation and then hopefully we're
going to have times to ask some
questions and ask their opinion about uh
the mapping uh between uh their concepts
and active inference and also more maybe
general questions about macroeconomics.
So very glad and very excited for the
talk and I give the mic to Dr. M.
>> Right. So in fact Nick here I'm going to
start off with a brief sort of
conceptual outline um and then um Robert
is going to give a a more detailed
technical summary. And I should say that
um I wish I was at the mathematical
mathematics institute at war because
it's a very grand place to be um but I'm
not that mathematical. So I'm I'm in the
behavioral science group at Warick
Business School and a behavioral
scientist by background. Um and in fact
it's probably a good place to start
actually because um an interesting
question for uh people interested in
economics from a behavioral point of
view is how do we make sense of economic
theory as it's currently practiced um
which assumes um for theoretical reasons
extremely rational and sophisticated
agents often have perfect knowledge and
perfect calculating abilities and they
they do perfect basian inference and and
um they maximize some utility uh each
one and then we put those agents
together and explain aggregate phenomena
as a kind of complicated outcome of all
those incred extremely rational agents
and the behavioral um spin on that is
always well yes but people aren't really
like that are they and you get all kinds
of irrationalities at the individual
level and perhaps some of those lead to
group level irrationalities as well. So
for example, booms and busts through
herding and so on. But the the fact the
the basic problem for trying to found an
economic theory is that if it turns out
that um the the agents that we're
working with are much much more uh
heterogeneous and complicated and not
particular
theory. Does that invalidate um or at
least throw into question um standard
economic theory? So an interesting um
strategy to to
persuade that worry um which is the
roughly where Robert and I have been
going although there are variety of
motivations you might use for this this
approach but this is a this is one of
them uh is to say well hang on um at the
aggregate level maybe um e economies can
work in quite a a predictable way even
if the individual elements within them
are extremely complicated and
heterogeneous and in fact we sort of
have to believe that because real
economists don't really think that um
that that they that players in markets
are perfectly informed about all
possible outside options and have a
perfect understanding of the
implications of all their choices. It's
just clearly not the case. And yes, um
at least on the face of it, basic
economic principles seem to be
reasonably reasonably um applicable into
the real world. Um so it it seems like
you have to really um have some belief
that there's an a way of understanding
the aggregate phenomena without
understanding micro foundations in any
great deal of deal because they're just
too complicated to understand. And then
a natural parallel that comes to mind is
not come to mind um to us um uniquely
because this has been something people
thought about forever at least a century
probably more is the thought that well
in physics
um you can say all kinds of aggregate
things about for example um the uh the
temperatures and pressures and so on
without really understanding micro
foundations terribly well. Indeed, of
course, classical um thermodynamics
arose before people had any real idea
about micro foundations and I think
weren't too sure about whether the
atomic theory was correct and really
basic things like this. So, it turns out
to be possible at least in physical
context to have an aggregate theory
without really understanding the micro
foundations you're working with. Um and
uh of course then it turned out
laterally later of course at least for
certain systems like very simple gases
you can figure out micro foundations and
miraculously um everything sort of fits
together. The micro foundations and
macro story can be beautifully uh
aligned which is a extraordinary
scientific discovery. But of course um
the classical the concepts of classical
thermodynamics still apply to all kinds
of complicated things like you know
human bodies and and so on which are you
where the micro foundations are
extremely difficult. So you if you're
trying to apply um thermodynamics to
biological systems you you're going to
struggle with micro foundations but
still you my body has a well- definfined
temperature and so on to some extent
anyway. So the thought is can we and
this is I say as I say not a unique
thought to us can we understand the
aggregate properties of economies um
without understanding the micro
foundations just as is possible in the
in the physical case and of course the
dream scenario would be there's some
direct mapping some sort of natural
mapping between one case to the other
and this is again something that people
have thought about for at least a
century um as a because because I've
seen so so many intuitive intuitive uh
connections um So it's feels like the
the something where there ought to be a
possible connection and people have
struggled to to to make that connection
rigorous and what we've tried to do is
to is to see if we can make that con
connection rigorous and one the only
other thing I want to say is that one
reason that we took the approach we did
is that we were inspired by um very some
very interesting work on the aimatic
foundations of thermodynamics by Lee
Ingverson
and the great thing about their approach
is that they have a clear mathematical
they sort of lay out the mathematical
principles which underly classical
thermodynamics in a way that doesn't
require uh any reference to any physical
notions. You don't have to worry about
you know heat or temperature or work or
anything. You just have these this
mathematical structure and indeed they
say in their um their papers that this
structure and principle could apply to
other things. Um and what we're so what
we're what struck us many years ago now
is that well this is if there is a
mapping to be created between these two
domains economics and and thermodynamics
then that abstract mathematical
structure that they've created ought to
be transferable and that's you that's
the starting point for the approach is
to try to to make that make that leap.
Um, and I think if we've, it's taken us
a long time to get there, but we I think
do have a fairly firm understanding at
least the simple cases of how that
works. Now, so I'll hand over to Robert
for a more technical talk, but at least
I hopefully give give uh listeners some
sense of why why we're trying to do
this. Of course, I should also say just
very briefly that the hope is both to
reconstruct some aspect of um existing
economic theory, but the dream scenario
will be able to but would to be able to
um to go beyond that to to to use this
method to explain systems that can't
really be explained in conventional
terms. Um so that one actually has a
richer a richer theory or at least a
complimentary theory to existing
approaches. But with that, I will stop
and uh and hand over to Robert.
Thanks Nick. So yeah, I'll present uh
some of our theory uh but also some
tests by simulations that have been done
by uh our student Tihang Luo.
So we deal with what are called exchange
economies. These are a very standard
concept in at least economic theory.
You'll find this in any textbook
in economics. So the idea is that we
have a large finite fixed number of
Asians and we have a finite number of
types of durable infinitely divisible
good. One of them we call money
and agents repeatedly exchange goods in
encounters
according to some
as physicists we'd say rules that are
just some behavioral characteristics.
say u the key assumption we make is that
this uh dynamics is assumed to lead to
convergence of probabilities at least
for the allocation. So we're not we're
not asking for the process to terminate
with some in quotes optimal allocation
but we are asking for process to
converge to some probability
distribution. So individual allocation
will keep hopping around but the uh
probability distribution will be a fixed
one.
Uh we start with what we call basic
economies. So ones with no barriers so
that uh a a part of good could in
principle transfer from any of the
agents to any of the other agents via
perhaps a long route.
And for these we assume convergence to a
unique equilibrium. So equilibrium
again means a probability distribution.
It's not a fixed allocation.
Uh unique given the total amounts of
each type of good. So obviously the
types of good we're supposeding are
conserved. So we get different
equilibria as you change the amounts of
good.
Uh but we're really interested in
multi-art economies. So where goods of
some types are constrained to some
subsets of agents which we call
components. Just think of an economy
that lives on two islands and maybe some
goods can't be transferred from one of
the islands to the other but other goods
can and maybe money can.
So again we'll assume conversions to
unique equilibrium. But now specifying
the total amount of each type of good
isn't enough because the amount of good
on one island can't change
either. So we need to specify a bit
more.
Then the question is what happens if one
removes some barriers or puts two or
more economies in some form of contact.
Right? So suppose it becomes possible to
move the good from one island to the
other.
And this uh one can regard as a basic
question in economics.
So we have an answer which is very
different from standard economics.
Our answer is that under some axioms and
one significant one that I highlight is
extensivity. So we assume that there's
some scaling symmetry of economic
systems.
Then each economy has a concave twice
differentiable entropy function we call
it s of its state. So the state is given
by the amounts of money and goods in the
various components that I talked about
such that when you put economies in
contact the total entropy cannot
decrease
and any outcome that increases the total
entropy is possible
until you reach uh a final outcome that
maximizes the total entropy then there's
nowhere else to go.
Contrast this with standard economics
where no economy would want to reduce
its utility. So if we think of this
entropy as maybe like a utility
and the final outcome would be a parto
optimal allocation accessible from the
initial endowment which wouldn't
necessarily maximize the total utility.
So this is uh this is the the basic
answer but I'm going to go through uh a
list of further consequences and
illustrate them by um Yang's
simulations.
So a first consequence is that each
economy has a financial temperature and
this is actually given by the reciprocal
of the partial derivative of the entropy
with respect to the amount of money in
the economy
and on financial contact money flows
from hotter to cooler. So this is part
of why we call our approach thermal
economics because we do have a concept
of temperature.
Each good say type I in an economy has a
marginal value new I which is just given
by this partial derivative
and the economy buys from or sells to an
external trader according as the
trader's price is below or above what we
call market price mui for the good which
is the temperature times this value.
Okay. So we can uh we predict which way
uh goods would flow if some external
trader says okay I'm willing to buy or
sell at such and such price.
Next consequence is we can make money
out of temperature differences. And this
is basically by making what's in physics
called carnocycles. And uh yeah, funnily
enough, I'm in Djang at the moment. I'm
in the uh mathematics institute, but
right next door is the institute caro de
borgon
in physics.
Maxwell. Yeah. Another consequence is is
we get relations between partial
derivatives. Like for example that the
partial derivative of the value of the i
type of good with respect to the amount
of the j is symmetric with respect to
interchanging i and j. In physics these
would be called maxel relations. In
economics at the level of individuals
such relations are called hoteling
relations.
So it's the same mathematics if you like
and it's due to the fact that the
entropy is twice differentiable and you
get a symmetry of second derivatives.
We also deduce because of the law of
non-decrease of entropy non- negativity
negativity of various partial
derivatives and matrices of partial
derivatives
and furthermore we get inequalities
between derivatives subject to
uh we can do derivatives with respect to
constant amounts as I've talked about
here or with respect to at constant
prices.
Okay, so that's maybe a lot to take hold
of, but to make it a bit more concrete,
uh we tested um the ideas on some
simulated economies. So the simplest
type that we used are what we call Cobb
Douglas economies.
Each agent has what we'll call a utility
function, though it's used differently
from standard economics.
Cobb Douglas utility is this product of
powers. The amount of money to a power e
to minus one times the amount of goods
to a power alpha minus one.
And on paralyzed encounters they pull
their belongings and they res
redistribute between themselves with a
probability density that's proportional
to the product of the their utility
functions.
So the idea is that uh this process will
bias the outcome towards increasing
utility
for the two Asians
but the there's a there's a probability
of one or other moving the wrong way.
And uh for this uh type of economy we
can pro prove convergence to
equilibrium.
So there is a probability distribution
for the allocation over the n agents
that is uh stationary with respect to
this process and whatever probability
distribution you start with will
converge to it as time goes to infinity.
Furthermore, we can prove using
basically the construction of the the
theorem of Lebanon Ingverson for this
case that the entropy has this formula.
So it's number of agents times log of
the mean money per Asian to the power
eater time the mean goods per agent to
the power alpha.
And from this we can deduce what the
temperature is. So just by
differentiating definition of
temperature it should be m / n * ea and
the price of the good here I'm just
posing one type of good as well as money
will be alpha m over e to g.
So, uh, Yiang put two of these Cobb
Douglas economies in financial contact.
Uh, one with, uh, an initial temperature
of 50 and the other 100. And he let them
equiliiberate, settle down a bit, and
then put them in contact at this time.
And you see that indeed the temperatures
move together. And we could have plotted
how the money flows. But the point is
the money flows from the hotter to the
cooler. Of course, there are
fluctuations here because the
simulations are just for finite size
whereas the theory is really for the
thermodynamic limit of infinite size.
Another simulation test we did was to
put a Cobb Douglas economy in contact
with a trader offering to buy or sell
the good at a given price. So we chose
the amount of goods in the economy to be
this 500,000
and at this time put it in contact with
the trader say the blue curve is when
the trader's offering a price of 0.9 the
market price is initially is one. So if
the trader offers a price of 0.9
well then the uh economy is going to say
oh that's a good idea let's buy lots of
it. So the amount of goods in the
economy is going to go up as we see in
this blue curve. But then of course the
uh situation in the economy has changed
the market price will have decreased and
it decreases to around 0.9 and then
fluctuates around there.
If we if the trader offers a price of
one well then there's no significant
initial movement. Price fluctuates
around the amount of goods fluctuates
around here. And similarly if the trader
offered a price of 1.1
then the economy is going to say oh good
let's sell to the trader.
Okay so there two uh illustrations
of the theory.
Another illustration is we can put two
of these cob Douglas economies in full
contact meaning we allow money and goods
to flow from between them. So here we've
plotted horizontally as the amount of
goods in the first economy and
vertically the amount of money in the
first economy and the uh total amount is
given by the by the opposite side of the
square if you like. So our initial
allocation
the first economy doesn't have many
goods and but it has more money than the
other one. So we start here and we let
them uh exchange uh the economies
actually have um different exponents in
their cobb douglas laws
just to show that doesn't matter and the
simulations trajectories look like this.
So the um there is flow of money and
goods from one to the other and then it
settles down around some point here and
the contours in this picture are the
contours of total entropy the entropy of
the two economies added together. So you
see that the entropy increases
to this maximum point
over here. We chose uh a different
initial endowment and we get the same
behavior. But uh interesting thing in
this is again to contrast with standard
economics.
What I've done here is to plot in uh
orange the indifference curve for
economy 2 and in blue indifference curve
for economy one meaning constant
entropy. So if we interpret entropy as a
utility.
So the standard analysis which called
the edgeless box
would say that uh depending on the
negotiating skills of the two economies
we'd end up somewhere on this paro
frontier. That's where there's no um way
that one can benefit without the other
losing something.
And indeed the maximum entry point in
this picture is in this interval of the
parto frontier. But over here it isn't.
Edge with box would say that you go to
some point up here. But when we put them
in contact they go here.
Okay. I mentioned uh that you can make
money out of temperature differences. So
just to briefly describe that let's uh
suppose we have uh two economies
uh we shall call hot and cold and we
have a ship economy that can shuttle
between them and the trader can trade
just with the ship economy and the
trader can put the ship economy into
financial contact with the hot or the
cold mainland.
So if we start here total goods is
horizontal. So, we start with 4,000
goods on the ship and a temperature on
the ship of 20.
Uh, then what the trader does is to buy
goods from the ship, which makes the
amount of goods decrease. We go up this
blue curve. Temperature goes up. That's
because actually the amount of money on
the ship is going up. And because it's a
Cobb Douglas economy, its temperature
goes up
and it goes up until the temperature
reaches 26, which is the temperature of
the hot economy. Then the trader
connects the ship economy to the hot
economy
financially
and uh decides to buy goods from the
ship. So it buys goods from the ship and
temperature on the ship fluctuates
because there's a random process. But
basically around 26 there's some money
flow also from the hot economy in order
to maintain this temperature until a
certain time when the trader decides to
disconnect from the hot economy and
carry on
um selling goods to the ship. We go down
this red curve until the ship reaches
the temperature of the cold. Then we put
in contact with the cold and uh buy
goods from the ship until we get back to
the beginning.
And in this process uh the uh trader
makes an amount of money
and in some sense is given by the area
of this suitably interpreted. So we
verified that. Okay, maybe that was a
bit long. In this one, we take into
account reality that the hot and cold
mainlands aren't infinitely large. So
actually, as money flows out of the hot
one, its temperature is going to
decrease a bit. And similarly, as money
flows into the cold one, its temperature
will go up a bit. So here we get a
spiral instead.
Uh maybe I should just skip skip these
things if they're too technical. But uh
this was an simulation to illustrate the
uh symmetry and negative definitess of
these partial derivatives.
So we took what we call a substitutes
economy where there are two types of
good but the Asians only care about the
total amount of the two types of good
they have. So that's why we called it a
substitutes economy.
And we also studied case of a confluence
economy. Again, two types of good.
The utility for an agent is given by the
minimum of the amounts of good. So one
good is useless without a corresponding
amount of the other.
And you can compute the entropy uh again
feasible to do this. But what we do is
we use Cobb Douglas economies as meters
in the simulations. And so we look at
these partial derivatives and we see
that indeed they're negative, definite
and pretty close to symmetry.
Uh another thing we do is uh putting
economies in contact and look at uh the
flow between them as a function of the
value difference. So actually we do it
the other way around because it's
slightly easier to simulate. We measure
the value difference of a given flow and
again we get some matrices representing
this and the theory says they should be
positive definite and indeed that seems
to be the case.
As uh Nick started out by saying, a big
motivation was to make a theory of
macroeconomics that allows for real um
behavioral agents rather than the
economist's ideal rational maximizers.
So we simulated one. So this is an
example that we call Busho economy after
Bush who inspired it. We suppose that
the utility for agent I depends not just
on their own money I but also on the
mean money that everyone else has.
So of course if we just have one economy
the mean money is not going to change.
But if we put two of these in contact
then the mean can change. And so that's
what we did here. We just again
confirmed that if we take two busho
economies
here and here the yellow and blue with
different initial temperatures and then
put them in contact at time two then
their temperatures will converge
together.
Um more recently one thing we've been
doing is for uh
uh what we call calorimetry by an
analogy of physics. So you might say,
okay, this theory is great, but for a
complicated system, how on earth could I
hope to know what the entropy function
is?
But it's exactly like in physics. Even
something like steam is too complicated
to do uh theoretical calculations for
the entropy as a function of say
pressure and temperature. So what do the
engineers do who run steam steam
turbines as my grandfather was?
They have steam tables. So they do lots
of experiments and they manage to deduce
what the entropy function is by looking
at how much heat is absorbed or given
out in various changes. So we do the
same in economics. Uh for a real
economic system this may be rather
difficult because you have to be allowed
to mess with it. Uh but for our
simulated ones it's easy.
So we uh measure the entropy by
integrating this relation for the
entropy with respect to uh money and
goods and the point is this integral is
supposed to be path independent. So the
theory says and indeed we check that and
find it's nearly independent and we get
a picture here. So there there is a
class of models and I think this is
something Navidid was interested in uh
for which uh one can prove that the
entropy is actually logarithm of some
what was called partition function in
statistical mechanics
and so this is uh
connects the macro theory with micro uh
but that's not fundamental to our
analysis. is
okay. So in principle for a um this
would be a good test if uh one I guess
some people do are big enough to be able
to play with an economy. Uh we've seen
notable examples um and if you're
allowed to play well then you could uh
try to measure the entropy function.
So a conclusion of this uh presentation
we've presented a thermodynamic theory
of macroeconomics
at least in the context of extensive
exchange economies
and the main things we show that they
have an entropy function and no
interaction can decrease the total
entropy. So a question that maybe you
want to ask us but I'm going to start by
asking you is how does this entropy
relate to the free energy principle and
active entrance?
>> Yeah. So um um maybe I'll let give I'll
just finish this slide and then let you
answer that.
So the uh publications we have three
that are out at least in two in archive
one in a journal.
Uh and um
the s is log z is something that's
nearly finished. Calorimetry we have
results but haven't written up yet.
And we're uh we've been thinking and
hopefully got some ideas about extending
to include things like manufacturing,
production, consumption, migration,
multiple currencies. And a big hope is
that we could generalize to
non-extensive economies because probably
unlike in physics uh
most economies are not going to satisfy
this scaling symmetry property. I mean
it's already a problem in physics. you
know, if you want to do statistical
mechanics of stars, then you can't apply
the usual thing.
Okay, so that's um a quick outline.
Well, thank you very much. Uh that was
incredible. uh and I was really
surprised by uh when I first saw their
paper uh I was really surprised by
the all the connections and all the uh
fantastic insight that it provides like
it really settles down some of these
ancient questions about you know trade
and tariffs and I'm not sure if it
settles down but it actually gives like
a a really interesting perspective about
these things uh instead of you know
people just arguing uh with words it
actually puts an equation there so very
incredible uh but at the same time I had
the feeling that you know macroeconomics
and thermodynamics
there are so much similarity between
them because they're kind of coarse
graining of millions or billions of
interactions and you know uh How why
this is like my question is uh why this
is this isn't the standard approach uh
or is it like in macroeconomics why why
don't
usually people uh use this kind of
language uh and this kind of approach to
model
uh complex phenomena.
>> Yeah, that's a good question. I mean
maybe we'll take turns we'll both offer
>> you go. I I'll add something
>> but uh you know from early days of
economics
people have uh thought and talked about
making the connections with physics. So
you know um
uh well a major player in this is uh
Paul Samuelson
um so he in fact transferred ideas or in
some con context he reckon the
economists had had them first I think
but anyway uh he he made connections
with thermodynamic thoughts um but he
didn't manage to make an entropy and in
the end he despared and decided maybe
there wasn't any reason there should be
an entropy function. So part of what
we're doing is um saying well actually
he shouldn't have given up. Um we think
that there really is an entropy function
at least for this class of systems and
we'd like to extend it
and I think yes I mean Sam Samuelson is
a very interesting figure. I think it's
right that he did he attend and was very
inspired by lectures possibly given by a
student of Gibb not actually Gibbs
himself.
>> That's right. Yeah. But but he he
explicitly in his Nobel Prize lecture
because he was really the most important
mathematical economist of the 20th
century. In his Nobel Prize lecture, he
talks a lot really a lot about
thermodynamics, oddly enough. Um and and
the degree to which he's his ideas were
inspired by them. But he the direction
he ended up going in was to focus purely
on individuals. So I think as Robert
says he sort of I'm sure he struggled um
to find the kind of um
a mapping which would give an entropy
function at the aggregate level. Um and
he didn't have English's um helpful
auction approach which is hiding in the
background of our our account. Um but
but what he did do is is f focus on
individual perfectly rational agents
interacting in a market. Um and that
that idea that we we could found found
macroeconomics on assumptions about
individuals became the standard way to
do things. And although of course
everybody continually says, well of
course we don't really believe these
assumptions about individuals, they're
not really true. They don't really have
perfect knowledge and um perfect
calculation ability etc etc.
Nonetheless, the theory assumes that
they do and and off it goes. Um so
there's been this enormous sort of
stream of mathematical economics which
under under undergurs really um current
economic theory which has taken this
very micro foundational approach but the
micro foundations are very specific
because they require this perfect
rationality assumptions. So in some ways
I mean things could have gone very
differently. I mean from a very early
stage it could have been that people
have made made a a more solid connection
um with a classical thermodynamic
approach and then there would have been
a parallel stream of work um which was
just focusing purely on the macro
perhaps not really worrying about the
micropics at all but that that hasn't
happened and and now I think there's
quite a lot of resistance to it so if we
when we talk to economists which we do
quite a lot um a very very common point
as well this is all very well but where
are your m micro foundation conditions.
I mean, of course, we have some if we if
we take the co Douglas economy
simulations, we can say, well, okay,
that's our micro foundation. Um, but we
don't really think that's right because
those are useful for saying um that the
theory makes correct predictions with um
you with with with a particular in a
particular simulated instantiation. But
the whole point is we don't want to make
assumptions that, you know, human beings
are really cop Douglas agents or
perfectly rational agents or any other
specific kind of agent. Um that would be
you that would be a um to to to to rely
on the micro foundation of story where
where we don't imagine such a story
could really be spelled out since that
humans and firms and government
regulations etc etc etc so in
inordinately complicated
thank you very much. Yeah. Uh
I I I think this is a fantastic honestly
very very interesting direction and uh
I'm really happy that at least you you
guys are uh working and we can enjoy
reading these papers. Uh so you you
asked about the entropy definition in
free free energy principle and maybe
Daniel can uh uh jump in here but uh
usually
uh in my experience people have maybe
share the same mathematical formula but
everyone has their own internal model of
what entropy really means and what it
really does. uh so I can give you for
example uh for me it's like it's it's
really uh something that agents consider
when there is degrees of freedom in
different explanations for their
hypothesis or for their model of the
world and uh there is this creates a
tension and free energy that is
dissipated when you come up to the
maximum entropy uh solution which is
like basically a kind of hyp hypothesis
testing uh kind of uh comparing
different hypothesis that they have the
same accuracy, which one is less
complex. Uh which one gives uh which one
has the least amount of uh
uh biases or prerequisites and stuff
like that. But yeah, there are multiple
other ways to describe this. Uh
I don't know Daniel if you want to add
here to this explanation. Uh
>> yeah well thank you for the presentation
and I think Navidivid your your comment
right there at the beginning about how
the core graining
between micro and macroeconomics is is
similar to that course graining between
the agent level behavior and the
aggregate collective phenomena.
So I I guess my question was when
entropy is used in this physical sense
of particles like the steam engine and
the course grading of physical states,
the decisions that they participate in
are
not necessarily
active.
they're following in a very
straightforward sense uh uh energy
gradients.
So what what kinds of
challenges arise in course graining when
those economies that you're modeling
could deal with memoryful
anticipatory
contrarian
mimetic agents
that undergo dynamics that aren't simply
like the bulk flow of temperature or
pressure.
Because when entropy is discussed in in
agent-based modeling and so on, it's
it's often the entropy of a belief
distribution
in terms of the basian updates of
cognitive beliefs that an agent holds,
which has some analogous formalisms
to that of the the gas engine and the
temperature exchange,
but in a way it's kind of transposed
into a different register.
I can say a couple of things that Robert
may have better things to say than I do,
but a couple of thoughts in terms of
bringing these approaches together. Um,
one of course is that in our world we're
just dealing with people trading goods,
but they could also be trading stocks or
security of some kind. And the classic
way that in economics people try and
relate those to beliefs is that they
talk about this concept of the arrow
debur security which pays you a dollar
when if some specific thing happens on a
specific day as it were. So, it's
basically a bet. So, you could have a
world in which people are trading bets
with each other, saying, "Well, I've got
this security." And someone said, "Which
will give me a dollar if this horse wins
a race, and I don't really believe the
horse is going to win a race, so I don't
think it's worth very much, but maybe
you think it is." Um, so you you could
have this you could you could have a
story, um, which we haven't developed,
but you could have a story where people
are actually, um, aggregating their
beliefs by by trade. Um and that would
be our our framework potentially might
apply to that. Um but we don't and and
then of course you you might well have
interesting um questions about um you
know what what that what what what the
um the aggregation of a of a large
number of people's beliefs how that how
that should should work and also um to
what extent that aggregate itself
behaves in some can be viewed in some
sort of meta level as kind of rational a
rational market. It's not really clear
to the extent that we'd have a story
which would uh uh but would generate an
idea about that the market itself as
being a kind of information processing
system but it' be an attractive idea um
because because what we're trying to do
is to think of the macro system as the
um the thing we're focusing on. So it
could be we can think of the macro
system as a kind of belief updating um
machine and so where specific bits of
information get fed in to different bits
of it because different you know
different people learn as they do in the
real economy they have different bits of
private snippets of information and
different bits of expertise and yet the
whole market as a whole is going to
produce um some kind of aggregate
outcome. So you're trying to you're
trying to see that I suppose we'd be
interested in seeing that process seeing
the whole system as as an information
processor is is closer to our approach
than focusing on an individual personal
brain. So of course that's still super
important how um individual brains work.
But here we're thinking well is there
some information it's interesting to
speculate is there some information
interesting information processing story
about you know whole um whole systems of
people when they can interact in a
market like way and of course um they
might not just interact in a market like
way because as you as you suggest Daniel
there are lots more complex interactions
they might engage for example they might
talk to each other or um observe each
other or think each other's reasoning is
flawed and so on and so on so there may
be many more complicated things going on
there which we don't have a a story
about but the hope would be that the
macro story might be somewhat at least
in some in some cases might be somewhat
independent of those details.
>> Yeah, that that was sort of my follow-up
question is what sorts of software or
theoretical or empirical developments do
you feel like this line of research is
taking you towards? Is there some kind
of retrospective
analysis that you feel could look at
indicators in economies that would
differentiate these formalisms and and
demonstrate their ability to provide
explanations and predictions? Or do you
feel like there's some kind of
manipulation sequence for a small
controlled or for an open economy that
again would uniquely
uh show where there's an explanation or
a prediction?
>> Yeah. Um for me the dream would be that
we can um
we can uh advise for example on what uh
trade agreements to come to. So while we
were going through Brexit, this was a
lot in my mind and I thought well if we
developed our theory sufficiently then
we could advise on what trade agreements
to come to because the idea is you
you'll see which trades would happen
under certain circumstances and um
so that's a long way partly because at
the moment our theory is only for these
exchange economies though as Nick has
said that includes a lot of things that
uh do approach reality.
Um but for example,
we don't well we haven't yet written
about manufacturing and production and
consumption migration and things like
this. So uh in order to really make some
genuine contact with real economics we
have to extend the the domain first
because you know it's the question
economists usually ask me is what what
predictions can you make about
economies. So for the moment um
we can predict for exchange economies
but then you need
you need an example that really is an
exchange economy.
So uh
the dream is that this will really shake
up the whole way that macroeconomics in
practice is done. Right? So every uh
government is going to have people who
will be busy trying to estimate
entropies and derivatives of entropy
and uh
work out uh what how to maximize
entropies.
So in um I mean previous direction you
you're asking how one can hope to
incorporate
uh complicated
agent behavior but I think as as we've
said that's really not an issue as long
as our axioms are satisfied. So
basically we need this convergence to
equilibrium and then we need various
other things that a lot of them are
really rather trivial. Um
but some have some substance.
>> Go ahead.
Uh no, I I wanted to ask like a very uh
like uh similar but maybe uh
uh related question at least like uh
when when you talked about the trade and
uh you know when you talked about uh
the end goal of uh this kind of modeling
and uh I was reading recently like a
economic book free to choose And there
are a lot of quotes from you know Adam
Smith in it and you know the market in
invisible hand that organizes this whole
operation. And then again for me it was
like a moment of h epiphany but or
something you know because in in free
energy principle we talk about these in
invisible hands in the in the sense of
self-organization
and how free energy gradients uh cause
you know uh mark of boundaries to form
or cause uh agents to behave in a in a
way or collection of agents to behave in
a way to get rid of these free energies,
you know, act against these gradients.
And that's how structures form you know
in uh hierarchically even you know like
in a in a biological system or uh any
kind of self-organization that we talk
about uh is kind of there is a gradient
of free energy uh and then uh
self-organization happens because of
that. And now in macroeconomics again
you we we we we have a lot of this
phenomena it seems that especially in a
free market kind of condition that uh
you know you have these B2C businesses
and then B2B businesses and then you
know governments that uh organize or
maybe sometimes interfere with uh this
kind of phenomena. Uh but the main main
question if you think about it this way
is that so where is this whole economic
machinery what kind of gradient is it
trying to uh eliminate you know where is
the gradient uh is it is it trying to
satisfy human needs at the end like is
this utility thing is a little bit
complex
>> and then what is the source of all of
these is uh low entropy
or uh available free energy that feeds
into this whole cycle and
uh I don't know if
>> yeah well these are deep deep issues I
think n but um but I think we have some
some sort of nebulous and not perfectly
formed yet thoughts on on some of these
questions. So I mean certainly the
notion of utility um I we're talking
about entropy as utility but that's not
utility um for specific individuals and
so it's a very interesting question um
is there is is the notion of utility um
as we're using it which is essentially
this aggregate property of the whole
system does that in any way guarantee or
tend towards an increase in actual
utility or well-being or happiness of
individual people and I think that's by
no means under is not is not in general
going to be true. There might be some
conditions under which it is. Um but so
that's you know that's a crucial
question for welfare economics of
course. Um another thing that's worth
highlighting is the this question of
self-organization. So you you don't have
a a deep a deep theory developed on this
at all but one of the things we're
really rather interested in is under
what conditions do certain kinds of um
uh organization organizations
spontaneously arise. So what why is it
that we we have firms why do we have
people suddenly constructing you know
laws creating states I mean obviously
all these questions arise in the same
way they do in biology and it would be
very appealing if it turns out that
whatever insights we have in a
biological case um there's a sort of
parallel between those and the and the
and the economic case so it would be
attractive if one can say if one thinks
that there's some maximum entropy
production story or possibly minimum
entropy production story or whatever
story you like that applies izing in a
sort of physics the interface between
physics and biology it maybe that's also
applicable um in in the economic context
too and that would certainly be
something interesting to think about and
just a final small thing is that the um
the invisible hand I think that you know
we it's very much at the front of our
minds here that um this this kind of
story is is telling you where the
invisible hand's going to guide you it's
going to guide you to maximum entropy
given the constraints you've got um
that's not necessarily going to be you
for the benefit of all human welfare but
it's that at the aggregate level that's
what the system is going to do that's
where Adam Smith's invisible hand is is
guiding us
>> yes so one one addition to the answer is
uh the the important thing I think is
production and consumption that's what's
that's what's driving the system
and this is where the intricate
structure
come from.
It's just like in physics, if you don't
drive the system, it'll settle down to
some pretty homogeneous uniform state.
But if you're driving it, then you can
get convection roles and all sorts of
things. And that's what we haven't yet
done. But um but to my mind, that's
that's where that's where really
economics is going to be
>> for sure. uh and the reason I'm asking
this uh about the utility function is
that the consumption part uh is a little
bit confusing for me because you know I
can think about different scenarios like
you can just put a put a like a oil well
on fire you know just consume all the
energy you know just waste it uh and
that wouldn't be an economic thing to do
uh it's not it's not a so it's it's not
obvious that this utility is like it
needs to satisfy some end goal uh that
I'm I I don't fully understand and then
>> I know I know we're nearly out of time
but we very quickly on that at least in
our world of exchange economies which as
as Robert says don't yet have the
driving forces of conduct production and
consumption but in our exchange
economies the agents do have a tendency
to um essentially try and increase their
own utility. So each agent is is this
you is is making exchanges on the whole
if they think they're going to benefit
from them with a bit of noise. Um so
that would be applicable I think in
other cases too. So if there were if
there was one use of the oil which is to
drive people around and they want to be
driven around and the other was just to
burn it pointlessly then the price
mechanism would kick in there there
should be a you know the people who want
to use the oil to drive around will pay
a higher price than the the people who
just want to watch the flames burn and
that will be that will that will uh mean
that we don't have a totally undirected
chaotic and of use of resources. So, so
it really ought to be the case that once
you have a proper theory of production
and consumption, which we don't think
we're that far away from, I don't think,
but we don't have that written down. Um,
then the whole point is that actually
create the kind of complex price
mechanism that people like and also
people in high and so on and um just
conventional economics really talks
about which should lead resources to be
distributed and used in the most
effective way. Um but most effective is
in in this story um from the point of
view of maximizing the integrity of the
entire system that does again rel not
necessarily solve the question of
whether the utility of individuals in
that world are actually being maximized
in agriculture doesn't solve the
utilitarian problem.
>> Yeah. Well, you know, our theory doesn't
require Asians to have a utility. It's
only these examples we made where
there's what something we're calling
utility just to make a connection. But
>> thank you
>> Nick and Robert for the presentation and
for the work. I hope it spurs many
people's creativity and curiosity. And
Deave, thank you for coordinating and
for catalyzing it. And we'll stay posted
on the research. Good luck with the next
steps.
>> Thank you so much for having us.
>> Thank you very much.
Thank you. Bye. All right. Bye-bye.